Guide to the Jesse Harrison Epperson papers, 1915-1959 RL.11883
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Jesse Harrison Epperson papers
1915-1959
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Epperson, J. H. (Jesse Harrison), 1889-1958
RL.11883
.25 Linear Feet 1 box
Dr. J.H. Epperson (1889-1958) was a resident of Durham, N.C. and director of the Durham County Public Health Department. Collection comprises correspondence, clippings, and photographs relating to his life and career. Subjects in the many photocopied news clippings center around Durham public health and sanitation history in the early 20th century, including efforts to combat communicable diseases such as tuberculosis and venereal disease in both white and African American populations. Includes 19 black-and-white photographs, mostly local news photographs, among which are 1920s views of downtown Durham, N.C.; interiors of the new Health Department laboratory in 1915; portraits of nurses and other staff, several of whom are people of color; and a 1920s group photograph of twenty local midwives, chiefly African American or multiracial women.
Biographical / Historical
Dr. J. H. (Jesse Harrison) Epperson was born in Kentucky in 1889. He received his medical degree from Oklahoma A&M in 1914 and joined the Durham City Department of Health in June 1915. In 1922 he was appointed Superintendent of the Board of Health, which oversaw the new joint City-County Public Health Department. He also taught Public Health for many years at UNC-North Carolina and at Duke University's School of Medicine. Epperson retired in 1954 after 36 years of service; he passed away in July 1958.
During Epperson's administration the Durham Health Department grew from three employees to over fifty, and he led major county-wide campaigns against early 20th century infectious diseases such as tuberculosis, typhus, polio, and venereal disease; he also instituted sanitation practices for local milk production.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Jesse Harrison Epperson papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from 1958-2002.
Scope and Contents
Collection comprises correspondence, clippings, and photographs relating to the life and career of Dr. J. H. Epperson, from his appointment in 1915 to the newly-formed Durham, N.C. Department of Health to his death in 1958. Subjects in the many photocopied news clippings (1915-1958) center around Durham public health and sanitation history, including efforts by Epperson and his staff to establish regulations for the safe production of milk, and to combat typhus, polio, tuberculosis, venereal disease, and other infectious diseases among both white and African American populations in early 20th century Durham City and County.
The correspondence chiefly consists of a few congratulatory exchanges between Epperson and Wilburt C. Davidson, Dean of the Duke University Medical School, where Epperson held a teaching position, and condolence letters to Epperson's widow. There is also one personal letter written by Epperson to his daughter and son-in-law.
Also in the collection are 19 black-and-white photographs (1915-1958), chiefly 8x10 inch Durham Herald-Sun press photographs, whose subjects include early views of Durham, N.C., 1920s; interiors of the new Health Department laboratory in 1915 with Epperson and staff; portraits of Epperson in his offices and at meetings; nurses and other staff, several of whom are people of color; and meeting and conference attendees, including a group attending a conference on preventing venereal disease. A nursing staff member who appears in several photographs with Epperson is an Elizabeth O'Kelly. Of note is a large 1920s group photograph of twenty local midwives, chiefly African American or multiracial, standing with Epperson and several staff on a flight of steps outside the Durham County Courthouse, where the Health Department was located.
African Americans -- Durham (N.C.) -- History; African American women -- North Carolina -- Durham -- Photographs; African American midwives -- North Carolina -- Durham -- Photographs; Communicable diseases -- North Carolina -- Durham -- Prevention; Health officers -- North Carolina -- Durham -- History; Midwives -- North Carolina -- Photographs; Nurses -- North Carolina -- Durham; Public health -- North Carolina -- Durham -- History; Public health laboratories -- 20th century -- Photographs; Racially mixed people -- North Carolina -- Photographs; Urban sanitation -- North Carolina -- Durham; Durham (N.C.) -- History; Durham (N.C.) -- Photographs; Durham County (N.C.) -- History; Black-and-white photographs; News photographs; Press clippings; Durham County (N.C.). Department of Public Health; Epperson, J. H. (Jesse Harrison), 1889-1958
- Biographical, 1915-1958
  Scope and Contents
  Includes a newspaper clipping announcing Jesse Harrison Epperson's appointment to the Durham, N.C. Health Department in 1915, and several resolutions and obituaries from 1954 that commemorate his origins and his 43-year career in the Department, along with other clippings and a certificate. Additional materials related to his career can be found in the Clippings series and Photographs series.
  - Clippings, biographical sketches, obituaries, and commemorations (Box 1)
- Clippings, 1933-1959
  The photocopied clippings in this series offer many details on Jesse Epperson's career with the Durham, N.C. Health Department, including his leadership in campaigns to eliminate tuberculosis, typhus, polio, venereal disease (VD), and other infectious diseases, as well as the regulation of dairy production in the county. The clippings thus provide some insights into the history of Durham, N.C. public health and sanitation programs, and public attitudes towards health and safety.
  - Clippings related to Durham Department of Health, city health issues, and Epperson's career (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1954-1959
  Contains a few exchanges with Wilburt C. Davidson, Dean of the Duke University Medical School, where Epperson taught for some time, and several condolence letters to Epperson's widow. Also includes one personal letter from Epperson to his daughter and son-in-law.
  - Professional letters and condolence messages (Box 1)
- Photographs, circa 1916-1959; 19 photographs
  The bulk of the photographs in this series were used to illustrate features in the Durham Herald-Sun newspaper. Although small in number, the photographs cover a wide range of decades, starting with three views of interiors of the Health Department labs (circa 1916), and a few images of downtown Durham, N.C. (1920). Editorial notes and occasional titles are penciled on the print versos. Of special interest is a large photograph dating from the 1920s of a large group of Durham-area midwives, mostly African American or multi-racial women, posed with Epperson and several of his staff. The photographs generally measure 8x10 inches.
  - Press photographs of the first Durham Health Department laboratory interiors and staff, circa 1915; 2 photographs (Box 1)
    These two 8 x 10 inch original photographs show wide views of the newly built laboratory interiors (1915), showing equipment and glassware, and featuring several staff, including Dr. Epperson. A caption on the back of one print identifies this as the Geer Building, where the Health Department was first located - in 1916 it would move to the new Durham County Courthouse on Main Street.
  - City of Durham, Main Street, near location of Health Department building, 1920; 3 photographs (Box 1)
    These photographs of Durham, N.C.'s downtown Main Street were taken during a holiday parade event.
  - Group of Durham, N.C. area midwives posed on outside steps of large building, mid to late 1920s? (Box 1)
    Photograph of a group of 20 Durham, North Carolina area midwives, posed standing in three rows on a flight of outside steps. From the architectural details, this is almost certainly the Old County Courthouse (built 1916), site of the Health Department offices. The midwives, mostly older women, are dressed in white caps and long aprons, and there are many cloth bundles, possibly their traveling supplies, on the steps surrounding the group. With the exception of one or two individuals, the midwives appear to be African American or mixed race women.
    In the top back row, also standing, are Dr. Jesse Epperson, Health Department Superintendent, Elizabeth O'Kelly, the Department's chief nurse, and an unidentified female who appears to be African American, in civilian dress. From the style of Dr. Epperson's suit, the date appears to be sometime in the later 1920s.
    On the back of the print is penciled, "Midwives - once an institution," and press photograph editorial marks.
  - People, 1920s-1930s; 2 photographs (Box 1)
    One small photograph is of nurse Elizabeth O'Kelly, on staff at the Durham Department of Health, standing with Jesse Epperson in an unspecified outdoor location, dated 1933. She also appears in the photograph of the Durham midwives. A larger circa 1920s photograph is of a group of men, possibly part of a meeting; a label on the print reads "Dubois / The Stevens."
  - Publicity and press shots of Dr. Jesse Epperson, other individuals, and Health Department-related events, 1940s-1954; 10 photographs (Box 1)
    The majority of these are Durham Herald-Sun press photographs of Epperson in his office or at meetings, with other individuals, and with staff. Some are captioned. One is of a group of attendees for a meeting on combatting venereal disease held in Durham, N.C. The last few are of Epperson's funeral procession, July 1954.
  - Photograph of Health Department laboratory, circa 1915 (Box 1)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Please restrict use to viewing and limit physical handling; photograph is cracked and fragile.